List of standard functions

Common functions

method defaultFromValue( from : T ) returns T

returns NULL value for argument type

method hasValue( Value : T ) returns Bool

Returns false if given parameter is null, true otherwise.

method stopDebugger( )

In DEBUG mode, stops browser in debugger.

method toString( Value : T ) returns String

Returns string representation of given Value parameter.

Bool functions

method defaultBool( ) returns Bool

returns NULL value for Boolean type

method defaultFromValue( from : T ) returns T

returns NULL value for argument type

method hasValue( Value : T ) returns Bool

Returns false if given parameter is null, true otherwise.

method isFalse( Value : Bool ) returns Bool

Returns true if given argument is false, false otherwise (i.e. argument is true or null).

method isFalseOrDefault( Value : Bool ) returns Bool

Returns true if given argument is false or null, false otherwise (i.e. argument is true).

method isTrue( Value : Bool ) returns Bool

Returns true if given argument is true, false otherwise (i.e. argument is false or null).

method isTrueOrDefault( Value : Bool ) returns Bool

Returns true if given argument is true or null, false otherwise (i.e. argument is false).

method toRawString( Value : Bool ) returns String

Returns locales-invariant string representation of given Value parameter as “true” or “false”.

method toString( Value : T ) returns String

Returns string representation of given Value parameter.

Date functions

method addDays( Value : Date , Days : Integer ) returns Date

returns given date Value after adding given Days.

method addMonths( Value : Date , Months : Integer ) returns Date

returns given date Value after adding given Months.

method addYears( Value : Date , Years : Integer ) returns Date

returns given date Value after adding given Years.

method day( Value : Date ) returns Integer

returns day part of given date Value.

method dayOfWeek( Value : Date ) returns Integer

returns day of week of given date Value. Zero means first day of week in current culture

method daysBetween( FirstValue : Date , SecondValue : Date ) returns Integer

returns number of days beween two given dates.

method defaultDate( ) returns Date

returns NULL value for Date type

method defaultFromValue( from : T ) returns T

returns NULL value for argument type

method getDate( ) returns Date

returns current date. Usable only from actions.

method hasValue( Value : T ) returns Bool

Returns false if given parameter is null, true otherwise.

method month( Value : Date ) returns Integer

returns month part of given date Value.

method toDateTime( Value : Date ) returns DateTime

Returns given date Value parameter converted to datetime.

method toRawString( Value : Date ) returns String

Returns locales-invariant string representation of given Value parameter in the form “yyyy-MM-dd”.

method toString( Value : T ) returns String

Returns string representation of given Value parameter.

method year( Value : Date ) returns Integer

returns year part of given date Value.

DateTime functions

method addDays( Value : DateTime , Days : Integer ) returns DateTime

returns given datetime Value after adding given Days.

method addHours( Value : DateTime , Hours : Integer ) returns DateTime

returns given datetime Value after adding given Hours.

method addMinutes( Value : DateTime , Minutes : Integer ) returns DateTime

returns given datetime Value after adding given Minutes.

method addMonths( Value : DateTime , Months : Integer ) returns DateTime

returns given datetime Value after adding given Months.

method addSeconds( Value : DateTime , Seconds : Integer ) returns DateTime

returns given datetime Value after adding given Seconds.

method addYears( Value : DateTime , Years : Integer ) returns DateTime

returns given datetime Value after adding given Years.

method day( Value : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns day part of given datetime Value.

method dayOfWeek( Value : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns day of week of given datetime Value. Zero means first day of week in current culture

method daysBetween( FirstValue : DateTime , SecondValue : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns number of days beween two given datetimes.

method defaultDateTime( ) returns DateTime

returns NULL value for DateTime type

method defaultFromValue( from : T ) returns T

returns NULL value for argument type

method getDateTime( ) returns DateTime

returns current date and time. Usable only from actions.

method hasValue( Value : T ) returns Bool

Returns false if given parameter is null, true otherwise.

method hour( Value : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns hour part of given datetime Value.

method hoursBetween( FirstValue : DateTime , SecondValue : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns number of hours beween two given datetimes.

method minute( Value : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns minute part of given datetime Value.

method minutesBetween( FirstValue : DateTime , SecondValue : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns number of minutes beween two given datetimes.

method month( Value : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns month part of given datetime Value.

method second( Value : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns seconds part of given datetime Value.

method secondsBetween( FirstValue : DateTime , SecondValue : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns number of seconds beween two given datetimes.

method toDate( Value : DateTime ) returns Date

Returns day part of given datetime Value.

method toRawString( Value : DateTime ) returns String

Returns locales-invariant string representation of given Value parameter in the form “yyyy-MM-dd HH:mm:ss”.

method toString( Value : T ) returns String

Returns string representation of given Value parameter.

method year( Value : DateTime ) returns Integer

returns year part of given datetime Value.

Decimal functions

method defaultDecimal( ) returns Decimal

returns NULL value for Decimal type

method defaultFromValue( from : T ) returns T

returns NULL value for argument type

method divide( A : Decimal , B : Decimal , Fallback : Decimal ) returns Decimal

returns float division A/B. If B is zero, Fallback is returned.

method divInt( A : Decimal , B : Decimal , Fallback : Integer ) returns Integer

returns integer part of division A/B. A must be >=0, B must be >0, otherwise Fallback is returned.

method hasValue( Value : T ) returns Bool

Returns false if given parameter is null, true otherwise.

method logarithm( Value : Decimal ) returns Decimal

returns 10-based logarithm of given Value. Value must be greather than zero, otherwise null is returned.

method logarithm( Value : Decimal , Base : Decimal ) returns Decimal

returns logarithm of given Value based on given Base. Value must be greather than zero, otherwise null is returned.

method power( Value : Decimal , Power : Decimal ) returns Decimal

returns given decimal Value powered to specified second parameter.

method round( Value : Decimal ) returns Integer

returns integer value of rounded Value parameter.

method round( Value : Decimal , Precision : Integer ) returns Decimal

returns integer value of rounded Value parameter with specified precision.

method toInt( Value : Decimal ) returns Integer

Returns integer part of given Value decimal parameter.

method toRawString( Value : Decimal ) returns String

Returns locales-invariant string representation of given Value parameter in the form “decimals.fractions”.

method toString( Value : T ) returns String

Returns string representation of given Value parameter.

method trunc( Value : Decimal ) returns Integer

returns integer part of given Value parameter.

Integer functions

method defaultFromValue( from : T ) returns T

returns NULL value for argument type

method defaultInt( ) returns Integer

returns NULL value for Integer type

method hasValue( Value : T ) returns Bool

Returns false if given parameter is null, true otherwise.

method mod( A : Integer , B : Integer , Fallback : Integer ) returns Integer

returns modulus of division A/B. A must be >=0, B must be >0, otherwise Fallback is returned.

method toRawString( Value : Integer ) returns String

Returns locales-invariant string representation of given Value parameter in the form “digits”.

method toString( Value : T ) returns String

Returns string representation of given Value parameter.

String functions

method defaultFromValue( from : T ) returns T

returns NULL value for argument type

method defaultString( ) returns String

returns NULL value for String type

method hasValue( Value : T ) returns Bool

Returns false if given parameter is null, true otherwise.

method indexOf( Value : String , Substring : String ) returns Integer

Returns index (from 1) of first occurence (from left) of Substring in given Value string. If Value doesn't contains SubString, returns 0. If Value or Substring is null, function returns null.

method indexOf( Value : String , Substring : String , FromIndex : Integer ) returns Integer

Returns index (from 1) of first occurence (from left) starting at FromIndex of Substring in given Value string. If Value doesn't contains SubString, returns 0. If Value or Substring is null, function returns null.

method lastIndexOf( Value : String , Substring : String ) returns Integer

Returns index (from 1) of last occurence (or first from left) of Substring in given Value string. If Value doesn't contains SubString, returns 0. If Value or Substring is null, function returns null.

method length( Value : String ) returns Integer

Returns length of given Value string. If it is empty, this function returns 0.

method newGuid( ) returns String

Returns new generated GUID (Unique identifier). It is using random numbers generator and produces valid UUID by RFC4122.

method regularExpressionReplaceString( Value : String , Regex : String , ReplaceWith : String ) returns String

Returns string with all matches of given Regex regular expression (javascript notation) replaced to given ReplaceWith. If Value is null, returns null. If regex is null or invalid, returns null. If ReplaceWith is null/empty, matches are removed from source string.

method replaceString( Value : String , ToReplace : String , ReplaceWith : String ) returns String

Returns string with all matches of given ToReplace string replaced to given ReplaceWith. If Value or ToReplace is null, returns null. If ReplaceWith is null/empty, matches are removed from source string.

method stringFormat( Format : String , Params… : String ) returns String

Returns string with format parameter replaced placeholders like {0} with corresponding parameter.

method substring( Value : String , Index : Integer , Length : Integer ) returns String

Returns corresponding part of given Value string. It starts at Index (from 1), and has maximum of Length characters. If any of parameters is null, function returns null.

method substring( Value : String , Index : Integer ) returns String

Returns corresponding part of given Value string from Index (starts at 1) to the end. If any of parameters is null, function returns null.

method toBoolean( Value : String , Fallback : Bool ) returns Bool

Returns boolean value of given Value parameter. When input parameter is not convertible to boolean (i.e. is not “false” or “true” in any letter-case), returns Fallback value.

method toDate( Value : String , Fallback : Date ) returns Date

Returns date value of given Value parameter. When input parameter is not convertible to date, returns Fallback value.

method toDateTime( Value : String , Fallback : DateTime ) returns DateTime

Returns datetime value of given Value parameter. When input parameter is not convertible to datetime, returns Fallback value.

method toDecimal( Value : String , Fallback : Decimal ) returns Decimal

Returns decimal value of given Value parameter. When input parameter is not convertible to decimal, returns Fallback value.

method toInt( Value : String , Fallback : Integer ) returns Integer

Returns integer value of given Value parameter. When input parameter is not convertible to integer, returns Fallback value.

method toLower( Value : String ) returns String

Returns string with all characters in lower case.

method toString( Value : T ) returns String

Returns string representation of given Value parameter.

method toUpper( Value : String ) returns String

Returns string with all characters in upper case.

method trim( Value : String ) returns String

Returns given Value string trimmed from both sides of white characters (spaces, tabs, and special non-visible characters).

method trimLeft( Value : String ) returns String

Returns given Value string trimmed from left side of white characters (spaces, tabs, and special non-visible characters).

method trimRight( Value : String ) returns String

Returns given Value string trimmed from right side of white characters (spaces, tabs, and special non-visible characters).

method validateAgainstRegularExpression( Value : String , Regex : String ) returns Bool

Returns true, if given Value string matches given Regex regular expression (javascript notation). If any parameter is null, or regex is not valid, function returns null.

Expressions

Expression is a way how to define some calculation. We use expressions in computed attributes, validators and actions. We define them in ActionLang.

Expressions contain arithmetics for NULL values. ActionLang is type-based, incompatible types have to be explicitly converted (by functions like ToString, ToBool etc.). Editor for expressions and actions has autocomplete (it may be explicitly called with CTRL+space), so it is relativelly easy to find out which objects are available in current context.

For simplicity, we don't use exceptions or error codes. All operations have defined result under all circumstances and in cases where some function cannot return standard result (ie. division by zero), they demand fallback value as a parameter.

Literals

string – can be entered enclosed in double quotes; if you want to actually have a quote inside the literal, you can use backslash to escape - \“. For this reason, you have to escape the backslash itself as well \\. You may escape other characters too, like \t but be mindful that the result is going to be generated to javascript where such characters may break the resulting script. This is true especially for \n and \r.

integer - number optionally preceded with minus (ie. 5, -5)

decimal - number optionally including dot and exponent (ie. 3, 3.5, 1.0e10d)

date, datetime

if it is needed to enter the constant in the code, enter it in format 'DyyyyMMdd' and 'DyyyyMMdd HHmmss'

boolean - constants true and false

null - in ActionLang, even null needs to have type. To test if something is null, you can use methods like HasValue or IsEmpty. To create null literal in the code, you can use methods starting with Default for each type.

ActionLang supports operator priority and changing this priority with parenthesis. Comments may be written between /* a */ or be started with // (these later ones are automatically ended by the end of the line).

Relational operators = <> < > >= <= in

Operations are comparing values. For null values we are trying to keep the rule that whenever some operation involves null value, result is going to be null as well. The exception is null=null returns true and null<>null returns false.

Because this “ANSI” approach to null values can make the comparison clumsy and hard to read, we have functions available that improves this a bit - isTrue, isFalse, isTrueOrDefault and isFalseOrDefault. These never return true, always it is either true or false.

Operator in tests whether value is contained in a set, ie. value in [“1”,”2“]. If value is null and there is null value in the set as well, it returns true, otherwise false.

Ternary operator

Ternary operator has syntax

condition ? expressionIfConditionIsTrue : expressionIfConditionIsFalseOrNull

It tests whether condition is true and if so, the result is the first part after the questionmark otherwise it is the second part (the one after colon).

Logical operators or, and and not

These operators can be used only for bool expressions.

X and Y | Returns null, if X or Y is null. Otherwise it returns false, if X or Y is false
X or Y | Returns null, if X or Y is null. Otherwise it returns true, if X or Y is true
not X | Returns null, if X is null; true if X is false or false if X is true

Arithmetic operators + - *

These are traditional operators for numbers (integer or decimal). They provide sum, difference and multiplication of two operands. If any operand is null, result is null. Division is done through functions divide, divInt, mod. There is no clear agreement on the result of integer division for negative numbers, so in such case, fallback is returned instead.

Access to data

Data are available in certain contexts. They are access by their names and potentially names of parent structures. These parts are separated by dot. Examples are name, this.name, subject.address.street. Current context name may be omitted while other contexts are available through their names, ie. form, globals, packages.

To keep generated code as close as designed application, some keywords that would class with used technologies are forbidden. For most artefacts that have Name property, if you would enter such keyword, IDE will automatically change it by adding underscore at the beginning. Other than that, the keywords of javascript are forbidden in naming things (see http://mathiasbynens.be/notes/reserved-keywords), keywords of actionLang (var, and, or, not, in, true, false) and context names (attr, collection, enums, functions, globals, metadata, this, packages).

Methods

It is possible to call synchronous methods (sometimes called as well functions) in expressions. If they are global, you call them directly by name (ie. length(s)) and pass parameters in parentheses. Parentheses are mandatory even if there is no parameter (in such case they are empty). If you are calling method on an object, you start with the name of that object instance, ie. addresses.count().

Custom functions

It is possible to define custom functions for the project. Function is defined in javascript and it declarase types and names of its parameters and result type. To use such function later in actionLang, you can find it on context functions, ie. functions.myFn(73) or myPackage.functions.myFn(73) if it is in different pacakge.

Such function should be pure function, it should be static, deterministic and it should not have side effect.

Data contexts

Data are available in various contexts, and their availability is based on where is the expression used. Expressions in data validator will have different context than expression that is written on the right side of assignment in action. Following table gives you general overview of these contexts and their purpose.

name | type | description
this | | Reference to current context, it varies based on the type of expression. Context methods can be called as this.<methodName>()
attr | attribute type | Link to current attribute. Available only in data validators.
packages.<packageName> | | Access to package metadata
> .functions.<functionName> | based on function | Custom function call
> .metadata.<entityName> | |
> .<name> | childStructure | Through dot notation it is possible to access metadata of given data element
> .caption() | string | Caption of given data element (metadata value)
> .isRequired() | bool | IsRequired of given data element (metadata value)
> .enums.<name> | |
> .<value name> | | Metadata of enum value
> .enumCaption() | string | Caption
> .enumValue() | string | Enum value that is stored in data attribute
> .globals.<jméno> | As a structure | Global attribute
<name> | |
Following properties and methods may vary based on current structure | |
> .<name> | | Dot notation allows you to get to the content of the structure; for data attribute it will return its value
> .owner() | | Parent structure
> .hasValue() | bool | True if attribute is not null or for if any inner attribute is not null
> .isValid() | bool | True, if all potential inner attributes are valid and all validators are valid.
> .validationErrorsCount() | integer | Number of validation errors on the conteiner and inner data elements
> .enumCaption() | string | Caption of current enum value (available only for attributes of enum type)
> .enumValue() | string | Value of current enum attribute (available only for those)
> .count() | integer | Number of items in the collection
> .collection() | kolekce | Parent collection for given data element

Lambda methods

Special type of methods can be called on collections or collection-like results. These methods are using parameter called lambda expression and are using current. This parameter will have the type of the item of given collection. It can be as well be renamed if you use syntax

var x => expression

These methods do not change the collection in any way, always returning new collection-like object (sometimes we refer them as enumerables). These methods can be used in binding.

.count() | integer | Returns number of items
.count(lambdaCondition) | integer | Returns number of items for which the condition is true
.any() | bool | True, if there is at least one item
.exists(lambdaCondition) | bool | True, if there is at least one item for which the condition is true
.selectFirst() | item | Returns first item; you should not call this unless you are sure there is at least one such item.
.selectFirst(lambdaCondition) | item | Returns first item that fits the condition. You should only call this if you are sure there is such item, otherwise you should test it first with exists
.where(lambdaCondition) | enumerable | Returns subset of items that fits the condition.
.orderBy(lambdaSelector, asc) | enumerable | Returns the items ordered by given criteria either ascending or descending
.clear(lambdaCondition) | integer | This can be called only from actions. It removes items that fit the criteria and returns their count.
.max(lambdaSelector) | decimal, integer, string, date, dateTime | Maximum
.min(lambdaSelector) | decimal, integer, string, date, dateTime | Minimum
.sum(lambdaSelector) | decimal, integer | Sum

Lambda conditions have to return boolean. Lambda selectors return some value.

Methods that return enumerable can be chained, ie.

form.collection
  .where(current.index() > 2)
  .where(current.Mass > 1000)
  .sum(var x => x.Netto)

Standard methods

Lets mention few standard methods that are worth noticing. For complete list check list of standard methods.

hasValue/isEmpty – check whether some data element is null or not

isTrue, isFalse, isTrueOrDefault, isFalseOrDefault – test value for true, false, true or null, false or null etc. They always return true or false, never null (unlike comparison operators).

toString – converts value to string

toDate, toDateTime, toBoolean, toDecimal, toInt, … – convert value to given type; second parameter is fallback value if the conversion cannot be done

getDate, getDateTime – return current date or datetime

defaultBool, defaultInt, … defaultFromValue – return null value of given type

stopDebugger – generate instruction for browser console to stop debugging at given point

Action methods

Following methods are only available in actions, not in expressions.

.clear() | - | Sets attribute or inner attributes to null. For collection it removes all items instead.
.isTouched() | bool | Checks whether the data element was changed by user since form start (or since it was reseted by setTouched method)
.setTouched(isTouched:bool) | - | Marks attribute as changed by user (see isTouched). Works recursivelly.
Collections and structures only | |
.fromJson(json:string) | bool | Fills the structure or collection from JSON string. Returns false if the parameter did not contain valid json.
.toJson() | string | Converts the content to JSON string.
.toJson(ignoreUnderscored) | string | Converts the content to JSON string, optionally ignoring attributes which names start with underscore.
Collections only | |
.addItem() | Item | Adds empty item to collection and returns it.
.removeItem(index:integer) | | Removes item from the collection on given index.
Collection item only | |
.removeMe() | | Removes item from collection.